A Guide to the WRVA Radio Collection, 1925-2000
Library of Virginia
- Series XI: Sound Recordings, 1929-1995, 630 compact discs. Duration: 317 hr., 40 min., 38 sec.
  - Tuck, William M., Campaign Speech, ca. 1945, (WRVA - 12); 1 compact disc. Duration: 15 min., 40 sec.
    Campaign speech, ca. 1945, of Lieutenant Governor William M. Tuck while campaigning for the governorship. Tuck praises Virginia's accomplishments and outlines his plans for education, health, agriculture, and the physically and mentally disabled. He promises to maintain the principles of good government and continued freedom from debt. He emphasizes his political experience and believes the election of a Republican as governor would be disastrous considering the overwhelming majority of Democrats in the legislature. Broadcast paid for by the Democratic State Committee.
  - Tuck, William M., Farewell Address, 11 January 1950, (WRVA - 19-20); 2 compact discs. Duration: 1 hr., 54 sec.
    This broadcast begins with commentary from Ray Kennedy and George Passage on the upcoming General Assembly session and the administration of William M. Tuck. Beginning on the second track of the first CD, Tuck delivers his farewell address, reviewing the accomplishments of his administration and criticizing the growing centralization of the federal government. After the speech, Walter R. Bishop, WRVA Public Relations Director, offers his thoughts on Tuck's address.
  - Tuck, William M., Governor Tuck, 6 January 1947, (WRVA - 66); 1 compact disc. Duration: 32 min., 36 sec.
    Titled Governor Tuck, this is a recording of Tuck's address before a joint session of the General Assembly, which convened to consider increasing "salaries of public school teachers, labor legislation and other matters which may appear urgent." The speech takes place in the Hall of the House of Delegates in the Virginia State Capitol, in a gallery "unusually well-filled" with proponents and opponents of both the labor issues and public educators' salaries. Tuck discusses the Denny Commission of 1944-1945 created with the goal of analyzing and improving the school system and says that despite gains, the Virginia public school system is in grave condition due to the scarcity of qualified teachers. On labor, Tuck discusses a bill he introduced supporting the right to work regardless of affiliation or non-affiliation with a labor organization.
  - Tuck, William M., Governor Tuck Speech, 7 December 1947, (WRVA - 65); 1 compact disc. Duration: 36 min., 51 sec.
    This is a recording of the keynote speech by Governor Tuck on the sixth anniversary of the Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor. Tuck is introduced by Richmond mayor, Horace Edwards. Tuck expounds upon Virginia's and Virginians' patriotic roles in United States history and discusses the importance of Virginia's "Declaration of Rights." He warns of subversive influences at home and the expansion of the federal government. Following Tuck's speech, attendees recite the "Freedom Pledge," which is followed by Langley Field's 564th Air Force Band's rendition of the "Star Spangled Banner" and other patriotic songs.
  - Tuck, William M., Interview, 29 November 1946, (WRVA - 64); 1 compact disc. Duration: 13 min., 55 sec.
    Governor Tuck is interviewed regarding his views on the current labor problem, meaning specifically a coal strike led by the United Mine Workers. According to Tuck, the coal strike, in which miners walked off the job without any regard for the public interest or public safety, was a very unpatriotic action. He calls for the repeal of the Wagner Labor Act, allowing states, not the federal government, to regulate labor. He calls the strike an insurrection, "a challenge by highly organized, blindly following minorities against law and public morality." He blames labor unrest on "the gang of dangerous and desperate despots" and politicians more interested "in enjoying the fruits of their office than they are in the public welfare." Interviewer also references Tuck's March 1946 threat to draft electric and power company workers into the Virginia Militia to prevent them from striking and asks him his opinion on John L. Lewis, the president of the United Mine Workers. Tuck also discusses the State Corporation Commission's charge against Lewis and the United Mine Workers for selling union memberships in Virginia, a suit first brought by the Richmond Better Business Bureau.
  - Tuck, William M., Speech, 22 October 1952, (WRVA - 38); 1 compact disc. Duration: 15 min., 45 sec.
    Recording of a paid advertisement of William M. Tuck speaking from WBTM studios in Danville, Virginia. Tuck announces that he cannot support the Stevenson-Sparkman ticket because of Stevenson's support of Truman's program. He criticizes excessive spending, Trumanism, the Fair Employment Practices Commission (FEPC), and labor unions. He believes that passage of the bill creating the FEPC would make life in the South unbearable. Tuck believes that Eisenhower adheres more strictly to the principles of the Democratic Party than Stevenson.
  - Tuck, William M., Virginia Association of Broadcasters Award, 10 January 1950, (WRVA - 570); 1 compact disc. Duration: 4 min., 44 sec.
    Recording of a ceremony and speech in which Governor William Tuck is presented the Virginia Association of Broadcasters (VAB) Award by VAB President, Phillip Allen of Lynchburg, for his wise and intelligent use of radio during his term as governor in order to reach the people of Virginia directly.
  - The Tunnel, 2 October 1968, (WRVA - 421); 1 compact disc. Duration: 24 min., 51 sec.
    Recording of a documentary on the 1925 Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad tunnel collapse in the Church Hill district of Richmond, Virginia, narrated by Derwood Felton. The history of the accident is documented, and includes information on the tunnel's construction, and the fear of its collapse in the 1870's. Includes comments by local historians and people who witnessed the aftermath of the accident, as well as information on the rescue efforts to save any survivors. The end of the recording features a commercial spot for the program.
  - United Press International Award Competition Entry for 1960, (WRVA - 515); 1 compact disc. Duration: 9 min., 20 sec.
    WRVA's entry in the 1960 United Press International award competition. Features news highlights as reported by the station for the year. Stories include the announcement of the state budget surplus by Governor J. Lindsay Almond and State Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr.'s reaction, as well as Richmond/Henrico County merger/annexation and the naming of the Richmond's negotiating team, a federal suit filed by the Petersburg Improvement Association against segregated lunch counter seating, and the legal ruling on the constitutionality of Virginia's "Sunday Closing" law. There is also a commercial spot for Jones Motorcar Company in Richmond.
  - University of Virginia Inauguration of Edgar Shannon, 6 October 1959, (WRVA - 365-366); 2 compact discs. Duration: 1 hr., 23 min., 20 sec.
    Recording of the ceremony surrounding the inauguration of Edgar Shannon as president of the University of Virginia. Includes speeches by Governor J. Lindsay Almond, Jr., Geoffrey R. G. Mure, warden of Merton College, Oxford University, and Edgar Shannon. Mure recounts Shannon's years as a Rhodes Scholar at Oxford University. Shannon speaks on the purpose of higher learning and outlines his vision for the university.
  - U.S.S. Forrestal, Christening of, Newport News, 11 December 1954, (WRVA - 184); 1 compact disc. Duration: 31 min., 27 sec.
    Christening ceremony, 11 December 1954, for the aircraft carrier U.S.S. Forrestal (CVA-59), at the Newport News Shipbuilding and Dry Dock Company in Newport News, Virginia. Includes the playing of the National Anthem, and comments by William E. Blewett, company president, and Admiral Robert B. Carney, Chief of Naval Operations, as well as Secretary of Defense Charles E. Wilson, and Secretary of the Navy Charles S. Thomas. There is also an invocation, and coverage of the actual christening by Mrs. James V. Forrestal.
  - U.S.S. Forrestal, Keel-Laying Ceremonies at Newport News, 14 July 1952, (WRVA - 183); 1 compact disc. Duration: 25 min., 45 sec.
    Coverage of the keel-laying ceremonies for the U.S.S. Forrestal (CVA-59), at the Newport News Shipbuilding and Dry Dock Company, on 14 July 1952. Includes the playing of the National Anthem, and comments by William E. Blewett, company president, Secretary of the Navy Dan A. Kimball, and Deputy Secretary of Defense William C. Foster.
  - Variety Plaque Awards, 17 February 1943, (WRVA - 73); 1 compact disc. Duration: 30 min., 32 sec.
    A recording of the special program recognizing WRVA for its contributions "to let every military man it could reach be assured that we Americans are 100% behind him." WRVA received the special award, presented by Variety Magazine, for its "distinctive merit in a field of war endeavor, for contributions to military-civilian understanding." The program provides an overview of the WRVA broadcast programs from various camps around the state, with samples from several programs Also included are speeches, such as one by Major General James E. Edmonds, Commanding General of Camp Lee; Virginia Governor Colgate W. Darden, Jr.; Barron Howard, Business Manager of WRVA; Irving Abeloff, WRVA Program Service Manager; and C.T. Lucy, WRVA General Manager.
  - Vintage Clip Collection for WRVA's 65th Birthday Celebrations, 1990, (WRVA - 496); 1 compact disc. Duration: 48 min., 55 sec.
    Collection of vintage clips from WRVA for use in its numerous 65th anniversary celebrations in 1990. Includes statements by C. T. Lucy, William T. Reed, Jr., as well as Dick Gillis announcing an upcoming election, Jack Clements and Harry Monroe announcing a portion of the 1956 edition of "This is Virginia," and a portion of the "Old Dominion Barn Dance." There are also commercial spots, and a clip of Art Linkletter's "Pillsbury House Party," Reverend W. Taliaferro Thompson giving the invocation on the station's 20th anniversary show, clips from "Music for the Day," and "Radio Scholarship Quiz," an interview with Bertha Hewlett, portions of Alden Aaroe speaking, and the agricultural report.
  - Virginia 1956, 31 December 1956, (WRVA - 142); 1 compact disc. Duration: 25 min., 57 sec.
    "This is Virginia, the 1956 edition". Major news stories of 1956 in Virginia hosted by Jack Clements and Harry Monroe. The segregation issue is the overriding theme of the year. Includes rundown of the segregation related events throughout 1956, including the passage of the Interposition resolution in the General Assembly, the closing of Seashore State Park, the special session of the General Assembly, the Gray Plan, the Stanley Plan, and Pupil assignment. Other major news stories include the school bond issue, the death of Alben Barkely at the Washington and Lee University Mock Political Convention, the 1956 Democratic National Convention in Chicago, the Republican National Convention, the Richmond city jail, and the Richmond-Petersburg Turnpike.
  - Virginia 1960 News Highlights, 31 December 1960, (WRVA - 377); 1 compact disc. Duration: 26 min., 35 sec.
    Harry Monroe and Lon Backman, WRVA news broadcasters, look back at the major news events in Virginia of 1960, including a Capitol Airlines plane crash, integration of Richmond's schools, the sales tax battle in the General Assembly, the arrest of Harry L. Donovan and the scandal of Richmond police officers being on his payroll, sit-ins across Virginia to protest segregation, Henrico County floods, the merger of Henrico County and Richmond, downtown redevelopment, Richmond city elections, an interview with Oliver Powers on the capture of his son, U-2 pilot Francis Gary Powers, the national Democratic and Republican conventions, and the beginning of construction on the Chesapeake Bay-Bridge Tunnel.
  - Virginia 1961, (WRVA - 232); 1 compact disc. Duration: 30 min., 58 sec.
    Hosted by Harry Monroe and Lon Backman, this recording features news highlights of 1961 and clips from previous shows. The date of broadcast is unknown. News stories covered include the Richmond police bureau investigation, Imperial Airlines crash, Hurricane Esther, Virginia elections, Richmond and Henrico County consolidation, demolition of the John Marshall High School, Sheltering Arms hospital donation drive, Civil War centennial observances, Richmond City Council proceedings, and the dedication of the new WRVA transmitter facilities.
  - Virginia Association of Broadcasters Awards Competition Entry for 1978, (WRVA - 431); 1 compact disc. Duration: 20 min., 43 sec.
    WRVA's entry in the 1978 Virginia Association of Broadcasters award competition. Features news highlights as reported by the station for the year. Stories include the U.S. Senate race in Virginia and the death of Republican candidate Richard D. Obenshain (1936-1978), and the subsequent nomination of John W. Warner and his victory. There is also a segment on the Richmond City Council, and the disappearance of Raymond D. Royall, a Council member, and his reappearance in St. Louis, as well as the criminal background of William I. Golding, another Council member. Also covered is the firing of Richmond City Manager William J. Leidinger by the Council. Other stories include the Richmond convention center project, stadium expansion plans, and Richmond police news.
  - Virginia Association of Broadcasters Awards Competition Entry for 1979, (WRVA - 432); 1 compact disc. Duration: 25 min., 41 sec.
    WRVA's entry in the 1979 Virginia Association of Broadcasters award competition. Features news highlights as reported by the station for the year. Stories include the snow emergency and winter storm that affected Virginia, the energy crisis, accident at the North Anna nuclear power plant and the vandalism and bomb scare at the nuclear facility in Surry, the strike at Newport News Shipbuilding, controversy surrounding Dana B. Hamel as chancellor of the Virginia Community College System, the purchasing and supply scandal in state government, Richmond City Council news, race relations in Richmond, General Assembly elections, Tropical Storm David, and various crime stories and accidents in Richmond, including a hostage situation at Southern Bank and Trust, traffic accident on Interstate 64, and fire in the Shockoe Slip district.
  - Virginia Association of Broadcasters Awards Competition Entry for 1980, (WRVA - 433); 1 compact disc. Duration: 27 min., 45 sec.
    WRVA's entry in the 1980 Virginia Association of Broadcasters award competition. Features news highlights as reported by the station for the year. Stories include the blizzard affecting Virginia and the summer drought conditions, General Assembly news and Governor John Dalton's legislative agenda, equal rights amendment supporters, the Richmond tax referendum, Chesterfield County school bond referendum, national political conventions and the election of Ronald Reagan, Virginia congressional elections, Henrico County jail escape, a story on the history of mass sterilization at a mental institution in Lynchburg, the nomination of James E. Sheffield as federal judge, and various accidents and investigatory segments reported on by WRVA, including a chemical leak, school bus accident, pollution of the Piney River, substance abuse in Chesterfield County schools, and state investments of tax monies.
  - Virginia Association of Broadcasters Awards Competition Entry for 1981, (WRVA - 436); 1 compact disc. Duration: 30 min., 30 sec.
    WRVA's entry in the 1981 Virginia Association of Broadcasters award competition. Features news highlights as reported by the station for the year. Stories include the repeal of the state sales tax on food and the budget surplus, redistricting, the U.S. Senate campaigns of Charles Robb and Marshall Coleman, the state budget crisis and budget cuts in Richmond and Chesterfield County, strikes by federal air traffic controllers and state coal miners, the death of Colgate Darden, Harry F. Byrd Jr.'s decision not to seek reelection, the merging of Miller and Rhoads with a New York company, the crash of a military jet aboard the U.S.S. Nimitz, and the 200th anniversary of the Battle of Yorktown. There also spots on WRVA's investigative reports on teen pregnancy, retreats by state employees, the gubernatorial race, and Richmond's homeless population.
  - Virginia Association of Broadcasters Awards Competition Entry for 1982, (WRVA - 437); 1 compact disc. Duration: 31 min., 20 sec.
    WRVA's entry in the 1981 Virginia Association of Broadcasters award competition. Features news highlights as reported by the station for the year. Stories include the inauguration of Governor Charles S. Robb and his first State of the Commonwealth Address, the rise in the gas tax to fund road construction, the major winter storm that affected the state, Richmond City Council elections, a train derailment in Richmond, the execution of death row inmate Frank Coppola, the United States Senate race in Virginia and candidates Owen Pickett, L. Douglas Wilder, Paul Trible, and Richard Davis, and the release of the toxic chemical pentaborane in Hanover County. There are also spots for various investigative reports by WRVA including drug smuggling at a Richmond terminal port and a series on birth defects.
  - Virginia Association of Broadcasters Awards Competition Entry for 1984, (WRVA - 438); 1 compact disc. Duration: 15 min., 7 sec.
    WRVA's entry in the 1984 Virginia Association of Broadcasters award competition. Features news highlights as reported by the station for the year. Stories include the snowstorm that affected the state, Governor Charles S. Robb's budget proposals and the raising of the legal drinking age, a large fire at a Richmond packaging plant, the severe drought in the state, anniversary of Martin Luther King, Jr.'s "I Have aDream" speech, and Richmond's city budget. There are also segments on investigative reports done by WRVA, including a story on the Virginia State Game Commission, an audit of Richmond's drug rehabilitation program, and child abuse.
  - Virginia Association of Broadcasters Best News Operation Entry for 1984, (WRVA - 557); 1 compact disc. Duration: 16 min., 1 sec.
    This recording contains sound clips of WRVA news coverage of the top stories in Virginia of 1984 including: the escape and recapture of six death row inmates from Mecklenburg Correctional Center in Boydton, Virginia; the Virginia General Assembly session; the proposal to extend Route 288; the election of Roy West to the Richmond City Council; the United States Senate election between Democrat Edythe Harrison and Republican John Warner; the presidential election between Ronald Reagan and Walter Mondale; the opening of Richmond's Sixth Marketplace; the nomination of J. Harvie Wilkinson, III, to the Fourth Circuit Court of Appeals; and the execution of Linwood Briley. Also mentions the WRVA News Documentaries focusing on spousal abuse, daycare centers, and Kepone.
  - Virginia Association of Broadcasters Best News Operation Entry for 1985, (WRVA - 582); 1 compact disc. Duration: 15 min., 5 sec.
    This recording contains sound clips of WRVA news coverage of the top stories of 1985 including: the James River Flood in November; the fire at the Southern Railway Warehouse at 13th and Main Streets in Richmond; the Virginia General Assembly; the inmate riot at the Richmond State Penitentiary over the scheduled execution of James Briley; the execution of James Briley; the dedication of Richmond's 6th Street Festival Marketplace; the march against crime and the soaring murder rate in Richmond; the march against apartheid in Washington, D. C.; the election of Gerald Baliles as governor, Doug Wilder as lieutenant governor, and Mary Sue Terry as attorney-general; Chesterfield County's bond referendum proposal; Hurricane Gloria; and the fire at a Southern States Feed Company warehouse at 1st and Maury Streets in Richmond. Also mentions the WRVA News Documentaries focusing on AIDS, teen suicide, and Richmond's political, social, and economic growing pains. Narrated by Tim Timberlake.
  - Virginia Association of Broadcasters Awards Competition Entry for 1986, (WRVA - 599); 1 compact disc. Duration: 15 min., 10 sec.
    WRVA's entry in the 1986 Virginia Association of Broadcasters award competition. Features news highlights as reported by the station for the year. Stories include the inauguration of Gerald L. Baliles and Charles Robb's last State of the Commonwealth address, General Assembly debate on the state lottery proposal and conflict of interest legislation, the Challenger explosion, Richmond City Council elections, violent crime in Richmond, gas explosion in the Manchester area, the conviction of Richmond stockbroker Clyde Pitchford, state highway improvements and tax increases, the execution of Michael Marnell Smith, and Alden Aaroe's 40th anniversary with WRVA. There are also segments on investigative reports done by the station, including Richmond's "slum lords," and group homes for the mentally retarded.
  - Virginia Association of Broadcasters Awards Competition Entry for 1987, (WRVA - 602); 1 compact disc. Duration: 29 min., 15 sec.
    WRVA's entry in the 1987 Virginia Association of Broadcasters award competition. Features news highlights as reported by the station for the year. Stories include debate in the Virginia General Assembly on the lottery referendum bill and approval of the referendum by voters, snowstorms and traffic problems in Richmond, various fires, a civil rights march in Colonial Heights led by Reverend Curtis W. Harris, flooding of the James River, shootings in Richmond and Petersburg, a leak at the North Anna nuclear power plant, local elections for the General Assembly, coverage of the Richmond Newspapers marathon, and clips on investigative series, including care of elderly parents, aging nuclear power facilities, and crime.
  - Virginia Association of Broadcasters Awards Competition Entry for 1988, (WRVA - 604); 1 compact disc. Duration: 15 min.
    WRVA's entry in the 1988 Virginia Association of Broadcasters award competition. Features news highlights as reported by the station for the year. Stories include snowstorms and travel problems in Richmond, Governor Gerald L. Baliles' State of the Commonwealth Address, a WRVA editorial on sex education legislation, Richmond City Council elections, the proposal on the location of Route 288 in western Henrico County, opening of the Powhite Parkway road extension, a hostage situation at an armed forces recruiting station, chemical spill on Interstate 95, a demonstration by inmates at a state prison, various local, state, and national elections, spots for investigative series on child leukemia and eating disorders, various WRVA editorial clips, and coverage of the Richmond Newspapers marathon.
  - Virginia Association of Broadcasters Awards Competition Entry for 1989, (WRVA - 605); 1 compact disc. Duration: 15 min., 40 sec.